Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
Today's דף daf is כ"ד Chaf Daled and we're continuing in the
discussion about רוב וקרוב. Rov and Karov. The משנה Mishna said that,
you know, if you find a pigeon near a certain dovecoat or
dove near a dovecoat or whatever, it you assume that it belongs
to that the owner of that dovecoat, which means you go by
קרוב, Karov, and that's put up against the statement of רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina that says you always go by the רוב, Rov, by
where the majority would come from and not by where the nearest
thing is. And there seems to be a lot of evidence that
you would go by קרוב Karov and the גמרא Gemara has a
way of sort of responding to all of that evidence in order
to support the position of רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina that you go
by רוב. Rov. So now we continue with that discussion and the
גמרא Gemara picks up, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
four lines from the top on כ"ד עמוד א', Chaf Daled Amud
Aleph, אף אנן נמי תנינא. Af anan nami tanina. We actually taught
a ברייתא Braisa similar that supports רבי חנינא'ס Rabbi Chanina's statement that
you go by רוב. Rov. What's
the ברייתא? Braisa? דם שנמצא בפרוזדור ספקו טמא שחזקתו מן המקור. Dam
she-nimtza ba-prozdor, sefeko tamei, she-chazakato min ha-makor. Okay, so now basically this
is about blood of a נדה Niddah and חז"ל Chazal in describing
a the inner physiology of a woman used a the משנה Mishna
says
משלו משל חכמים באשה החדר והפרוזדור והעליה. Mashlu mashal chachamim be-isha, ha-cheder
ve-ha-prozdor ve-ha-aliya. All right, so which is this house, right. So so
the חדר, Cheder, which is the inner room, okay, that's basically the
uterus. Okay, the only blood from the uterus is טמא. Tamei. All
right, so therefore the assumption is that the פרוזדור, Prozdor, which is
the antechamber, the assumption is is that that's referring to the vaginal
canal and that this would be the פרוזדור. Prozdor. Okay, and the
question is if you have blood here, right, should use red, right,
so presumably it came from the uterus and it's דם נדה Dam
Niddah and it's טמא. Tamei. דם נדה Dam Niddah is טמא Tamei
even before it exits the woman's body, even once it leaves the
uterus. So the question is what is this עליה? Aliya? What is
this second story that is above the חדר Cheder here, right, that
is nobody really knows what they were referring to, but there's this
some other some other type of a of a place where blood
could come from and then it says there's actually a לול פתוח,
Lul patuach, a what do you call it, a like a certain
type of a what's a לול, Lul, like
a a like a, נו nu what, anyway, some type of an
opening, okay, is open, a tube, thank you, that would get that
that blood from the עליה, Aliya, which is not דם טמא, Dam
tamei, could come in and it could come into the פרוזדור. Prozdor.
Okay, so the question is if you find blood here in the
vaginal canal, you assume it's דם נדה Dam Niddah because most blood
comes from the חדר, Cheder, most blood comes from the uterus, the
uterine lining when the woman has her menstrual period. Even though, says
the גמרא, Gemara, so you see you go by רוב, Rov, that's
where most of the blood comes from, even though the עליה Aliya
is closer and it could be coming from the עליה, Aliya, nevertheless
you go by רוב. Rov. So nobody really understands what this עליה
Aliya is and what the גמרא'ס Gemara's concerned about, but for our
purposes, this is used to prove that you go by רוב Rov
and not by קרוב. Karov. Now I will say that actually the
best explanation for those who are curious about what the what the
עליה Aliya might refer to and what the פרוזדור Prozdor might refer
to, in another גמרא, Gemara, and this idea has come up in
the some אחרונים Acharonim but they rejected it, in another גמרא Gemara
they're dealing with animals, because the גמרא Gemara says that a cow
doesn't have a פרוזדור. Prozdor. And what a cow doesn't have is
a cow doesn't have the external labia of the of the vagina.
So therefore that gives a reason to think that the פרוזדור Prozdor
is not the inner vaginal canal, but the פרוזדור Prozdor is actually
the sort of the space created outside of the body by the
labia. And if that's true, right, so if this is the opening
and this is where so you actually have, right, the opening of
the of the what do you call it, of the for the
for the urine,
what's that opening called, the urethra, right, anyway is there. So that
actually now makes sense, because if we're talking on the outside of
the body, right, blood could come from the from the from the
urethra if there's some blood in the urine, right, and then it
could be found out here. So that actually understand that a lot
better. Is that clear what I'm drawing here? Right, so if blood
is if this is the פרוזדור, Prozdor, the external, so most of
the time the blood is coming from the vagina and it's and
it's and from the and it's from the uterus. But it is
possible that blood could actually be coming from the opening of the
urethra and it could be in the urine. Okay, so that actually
that issue now makes a lot of sense, right, what is this
upper what is this upper level, what is this לול Lul that's
פתוח, patuach, right, that actually makes a lot of sense. But if
you're talking inside the body, nobody knows what the עליה Aliya is.
and how you're supposed to be getting blood from the עליה aliyah
into the פרוזדור. prozdor.
I'd just say it's the latter one.
Yeah, because there's evidence in other sources that it makes an enormous
amount of sense to say it is, but for instance more
internal. Exactly. And that's what I'm saying, because of other evidence when
the גמרא Gemara is talking about the פרוזדור prozdor by a woman,
it sounds like it's internal, but then it makes it incomprehensible what
the עליה aliyah is. But when it's talking about a cow, it
sounds like the פרוזדור prozdor is external and if we were to
interpret that in this case, it would actually make a lot of
sense. But I have to get back into the סוגיא, sugya, but
the reason I'm putting it there is because it's the most compelling
explanation. But in general although some did realize that as a possibility,
it's rejected because of other evidence.
Yes, and they're identical in color and everything?
Yeah, that's also true. If you can see by the look of
the blood then that's in general a question when there's ways of
ascribing blood to a different source, to a מכה maka or whatever
and by the way it looks, that can add to evidence. But
we're talking in assuming the case where there isn't any indication in
terms of that.
Are they identical whether it comes from the עליה aliyah or...
No, because the blood, no, because it very well might not. Because
blood coming from the uterus is part of the uterine lining which
has all this other stuff mixed up with it, so it's not
the same color as like blood that comes from like a cut
or a wound. But we would have to be talking in a
case where there's not evidence from how it looks. Yes.
No, so in other words, it's a situation theoretically when there's blood
in the urine as it were?
Yes, but that's if we assume the פרוזדור prozdor is external. Right,
that actually makes a lot of sense. Okay, this nobody knows what
exactly we talking about. But either way, the גמרא's Gemara's point is,
ah, you see, that looks like it's an opening. Anyway you see
that we are, you see that we're going by רוב rov and
not by קרוב. karov. That's sort of the גמרא's Gemara's argument. So
let's take a look.
Okay, תנינא, אף אנן נמי תנינא. Tanina, af anan nami tanina. דם
הנמצא בפרוזדור ספקו טמא. Dam hanimtza baprozdor sfeko tamei.
It's doubtful and because there is a doubt, but nevertheless you rule
that it is טמא. tamei. שחזקתו מן המקור, Shechezkatzo min hamakor, you
can assume that it is coming from the uterus. ואף על גב
דאיכא עליה דמקרבא. Ve'af al gav d'ika aliyah d'mekarva. Now the עליה
aliyah though is closer and nevertheless you go by רוב. rov. So
אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so Rava said back, רוב ומצוי
קאמרת? rov u'matzuy ka'amart? Oh,
that's not just a רוב. rov. That's a רוב rov and it's
מצוי, matzuy, it's like most prevalent, right? So a, just quantity-wise more
blood is in the uterus than is in this עליה. aliyah. And
secondly, but it's the natural thing is that the blood comes out
of the uterus. So it's not just a question of quantity. It's
like what's more prevalent.
רוב ומצוי, rov u'matzuy, לית דמאן דפליג, leit deman d'palig, nobody debates
that.
I'm sensing that there are two concepts, but it seems how are
they...
Because, because for example, the cases before we had, you have a
nearby dovecote and you have one that's a mile away, but they
have 500 doves there. Okay. So that's just there is more in
terms of quantity, but you're not directly saying that, let's say you
actually have, that would be רוב. rov. But let's say you had
a reality that you knew that this place where this dove was
found was a place where on a normal day, you know, 100
birds would fly by and 95% of them were from the bigger
dovecote. That would be מצוי. matzuy. You actually have the sort of
the, you know, it...
you have the actual, what's the best way to say this, right,
meaning it's like the practice, practice is the wrong word here, but
the pattern has been established that the majority, that it's most prevalent
it comes from this source rather than that source. In the normal
case of רוב, rov, no, רוב rov is just the numbers. You
just know that there's a much bigger operation a mile down the
road. You don't know that in this location it's more prevalent for
there to be those birds than that bird. That's actually what you're
trying to get at. You're trying to get at the question of
where is it more prevalent that it would come from? Is it
more prevalent would come from the nearby place or more prevalent would
come from the more numerous place? That's רוב rov versus קרוב. karov.
Here מצוי matzuy is you know that it's more prevalent. The actual
like evidence shows that most of the time doves that are flying
in this area are coming from place X. So here the majority
of blood is here, there's very little blood in the עליה aliyah
if at all, and under normal circumstances all the blood that comes
through the פרוזדור prozdor is coming from the חדר. cheder.
Yeah, I was just going to say they were talking about like
real what's the רוב rov of blood in the body, it's not
the uterus either. Right. The רוב rov is somewhere else.
Right. But of these two competing sources, right, I mean if you
want to go through the thing, right, this is the bigger
dovecote operation, this is the closer one, and this is the path
in where the dove is found. And we know, it's not just
we know where more of the doves are, we know that actually
the majority of doves that fly over this area are coming from
this location.
So right, so I'm saying like the parallel of the dovecote that's
far away would be רוב rov where they don't fly here would
be like...
of the blood in the body. Right, exactly. Okay, so, so רוב
ומצוי כמרתא rov u-matzui kamarta one minute. We're talking here not just
where the majority is, but what's prevalent, okay, where it like you
know, what's the פרט, prat, what's the natural way that, you know,
it sort of, it plays out in reality. רוב ומצוי ליכא למאן
דאמר, rov u-matzui leka leman d'amar, nobody would say there you go
by קרוב, karov, דתניא רבי חייא, detanya Rabbi Chiya, because Rabbi Chiya
teaches, דם הנמצא בפרוזדור חייבין עליו על ביאת מקדש. dam hanimtzah baprozdor
chayavin alav al biat mikdash. It's not just a ספק, safek, it's
treated as a ודאי, vaday, that if you find this blood in
the פרוזדור, prozdor, and then, you know, the woman were to enter
into the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, she'd be חייב כרת, chayav karet,
or if a man had sex with her and he was טמא,
tamei, he'd be חייב כרת. chayav karet. It would be considered a
ודאי נדה. vaday niddah. ושרפין עליו את התרומה, vesorfim alav et haterumah,
if you touch תרומה, terumah, you were treated as ודאי תרומה, vaday
terumah, you wouldn't treat it as a ספק תרומה, safek terumah, as
ודאי תרומה טמאה, vaday terumah tmei'ah, you would burn it. Okay, ואמר
רבא, ve'amar Rava, and Rava says, שמע מינה מדרבי חייא תלת. shma
mina mid'Rabbi Chiya tlat. Now, okay, so, so therefore that's why. The
reason is, is because it is not just that's a majority quantity
of blood, but you actually know in practice most of the blood
flows through the פרוזדור prozdor from the חדר. cheder. Okay, ואמר רבא,
ve'amar Rava, now Rava also says, שמע מינה מדרבי חייא תלת, shma
mina mid'Rabbi Chiya tlat, we can infer from Rabbi Chiya three things,
who says that we treat it as ודאי טמא. vaday tamei. שמע
מינה רוב וקרוב הלכה אחר הרוב. shma mina rov vekarov halcha achar
harov. If it's between רוב וקרוב, rov vekarov, you go by רוב,
rov, you treat it. ושמע מינה רובא דאורייתא, veshma mina ruba d'oraita,
that
the principle of going by רוב rov and treating it as a
ודאי, vaday, not as a ספק, safek, is biblical, because you treat
this woman as ודאי טמאה, vaday tmei'ah, as definitely
טמא. tamei. ושמע מינה מסייע ליה לרבי זירא, veshma mina mesayei lei
l'Rabbi Zeira, we hold like רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. דאמר רבי זירא,
d'amar Rabbi Zeira, because Rabbi Zeira said, אף על פי שדלתות מדינה
נעולות נעולות, af al pi shedaltot hamedina ne'ulot ne'ulot, even though the
stores of, the gates of the city are closed. What is this
talking about? So this is a famous other example of going by
רוב, rov, which you might have heard about, which is, you have
nine, you have, you find a piece of meat in the street,
okay, here's your piece of meat, and you don't know if it's
kosher or טרף. treif. And you have, right in, in the city
nine stores, far as I have six, seven, eight, you have nine
stores that sell kosher meat, and one store that sells טרף. treif.
Okay, ignore my pictures. And you find this piece of meat, and
you don't know where it's from. So you go by רוב rov
and you assume it's kosher and you can eat it. Now, that's
okay, even if now that might even be if it's okay, so
that's going by רוב. rov. Now, there's a question though, some opinions
in the גמרא Gemara don't like the idea that you could just
go by one רוב rov and eat this meat which might be
טרף. treif. So what they want to say is, also we're talking
that the doors of the city are open, and since the doors
of the city are open, and there's a majority of kosher, you
know, Jewish communities in the surrounding neighborhood, so it's two רוב. rov.
It's the רוב rov in this city plus the רוב rov of
where the meat could come from from outside the city. Okay, of
course once you say you have to put limits on it because
the whole world is majority non-Jewish, but anyway, in the immediate neighborhood.
So they want to limit it to two רוב. rov. Only then
can you go by it. And comes רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira and
says no, even if the doors of the city are closed and
you only have this one רוב, rov, that's enough to let you
eat this meat. So you go by רוב rov even if you
only have one רוב, rov, and you go by it even against
קרוב, karov, and you go by it and you treat it as
a ודאי, vaday, and both to be strict that the woman, you
know, if she be, treated as a ודאי נדה, vaday niddah, she'd
bring a קרבן, korban, you wouldn't say it's maybe חולין בעזרה, chullin
ba'azarah, and would be ודאי vaday to be lenient, you would allow
the person to eat the piece of meat. Okay, so you go
by רוב rov and it's דאורייתא de'oraita and you treat it as
a ודאי vaday even with only one
רוב. rov. Yes.
Is
there like
an amount that you need to be רוב rov in order for
it to count? Meaning if it was two kosher butcher shops and
one טרף? treif?
Yeah, so that's true, meaning nine and one is like is a
little bit tipping the scale. So the basic, so there are different
הלכות halachot by רוב rov of,
you go by רוב rov even if it's a small רוב, rov,
although sometimes you know the question how small, 51 percent. You certainly
don't need nine against one. There is a question in general in
הלכות אחרי הרוב hilchot acharei harov about the way it's phrased is
usually how not how big the רוב rov is but how big
the... How big the מיעוט Miut is. Is it a מיעוט המצוי?
Miut Hamatzui?
Is it a prevalent מיעוט Miut or a מיעוט שאינו מצוי, Miut
She'eino Matzui, a rare מיעוט? Miut? Okay, and the difference usually between
those is that first of all, what's the difference? It's usually assumed
מיעוט שאינו מצוי Miut She'eino Matzui is going to be less than
ten percent or some say less than five percent. Okay, so if
you have a big רוב, Rov, 90, 95 percent, then the difference
between these two is in this case if the מיעוט Miut is
more substantial, then you're supposed to do more investigation if possible. There's
a חיוב לברר. Chiyuv Levarer. Like if you can go ahead and
make a few phone calls, do a little investigation, you can't just
סתם Stam rely on the רוב Rov if it's a non-trivial possibility
that it might be a problem. But once it's considered to be
a trivial possibility, you can go on the רוב Rov even if
it's אפשר לברר. Efshar Levarer. That's why for example when you שחט
Shacht an animal, you only have to check the lungs for טרפות
Treifos and not the other organs because it's considered that the likelihood
that there's a טרפה Treifah in the lungs is a מיעוט Miut
is a מיעוט המצוי. Miut Hamatzui. So you have to check it.
But the likelihood there's a טרפה Treifah in the other organs is
a מיעוט שאינו מצוי, Miut She'eino Matzui, right? Because and you can
imagine if you had to check every single organ like the price
of meat would go up so much more, right? Because of the
amount of effort. So that's actually, but the basic point is you
don't need nine against one. That's true. Okay, but whether 51 percent
is enough, there's some bit of question about that.
Is distance taken into account where that meat is to the non-kosher
store?
Yes, so based on what we're saying about רוב Rov and קרוב,
Karov, you would say even if it's closer to the non-kosher store,
although that's not stated explicitly, but in principle that would be true.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara just has one question. One minute, says the גמרא. Gemara. דאפילו
הכי חזינן בתר
רובא. De'afillu hachi chazinan batar ruba. I'm sorry, I skipped a line.
דאמר רב זביד אבבי דשינשא מדינא נעולות. De'amar Rav Zevid avavei d'shinsha
medina ne'ulot.
Even though there's no external רוב, Rov, one רוב Rov is enough.
דהא אשה דכי דלא זזה מדינא נעולות דמיא. Deha ishah dechi d'lo
zazah medina ne'ulot damya.
This woman is like the doors of the city are closed. Again,
very funny continuing with that house and doors type of imagery, but
no blood is coming from the outside, okay? ואפילו הכי חזינן בתר
רובא. Va'afillu hachi chazinan batar ruba.
And nevertheless you go by רוב, Rov, meaning there's only one רוב,
Rov, right? The רוב Rov here against the קרוב. Karov. And nevertheless
you assume she's טמאה, Tmeiah, so you see one רוב Rov wins
out against קרוב. Karov. You don't need two רובs. Rov So now
the גמרא Gemara says one minute. But why are we using that
to teach a general principle of רוב Rov and קרוב? Karov? We
just said the case of the woman was more than just רוב.
Rov. והא רבה הוא דקאמר רוב ומצוי לית דאמר. Veha Rabbah hu
deka'amar rov u'matzui leit d'amar. רבה Rabbah said that רוב ומצוי Rov
u'matzui goes without saying. So like this isn't a standard case of
רוב Rov against קרוב, Karov, you actually have like a pattern that's
established. You know that that's how it happens most of the time.
הדר ביה רבה מהאי. Hadar beih Rabbah meihai. No, רבה Rabbah retracted
that. So the question is like which one did he retract? Did
he retract the רוב ומצוי Rov u'matzui or did he retract the
idea that this is
to use this as an example of רוב Rov and קרוב? Karov?
So I didn't see רש"י Rashi or תוספות Tosafos
commenting on it.
I didn't see if your גמרא Gemara sort of say which one
it's assuming רבה Rabbah retracted? Because the רוב Rov and קרוב Karov
position, the רוב ומצוי Rov u'matzui position certainly is the one that
makes more sense to...
does it claim which way he's retracting, which way it's assumed he's
retracting?
Says he retracted the rejection of אביי's Abaye proof.
He retracted the rejection, meaning he thought that not to give it
extra weight because it's רוב ומצוי. Rov u'matzui. Yeah, that's the way
it sounds. But of course the problem is that it actually makes
a lot of sense that the מצוי Matzui makes it a very
different type
of a what do you call it, of a weight. Once you're
not only רוב, Rov, but it's רוב ומצוי, Rov u'matzui, obviously that
should completely sort of change the equation. But here it's sounding like
that in the end רבה Rabbah decided, no, you know, somebody who
goes by קרוב Karov could go by קרוב Karov even against רוב
ומצוי, Rov u'matzui, although that's really much harder to
understand once a pattern has been established. It notes here that possibly
the גמרא Gemara doesn't explain the reason and says possibly the reason
is that frequency is merely due to majority anyway.
Yeah, but the way we've been explaining it, if the frequency is
direct evidence of it, right, but that's true. Okay, anyway, so while
the גמרא Gemara makes... רבה Rabbah makes a good point that if
it's not just that you know there's a majority, but you've actually
seen a pattern. And once you've seen a pattern, everybody should agree
that you go by that and not by קרוב. Karov. At the
end it sounds like רבה Rabbah is categorizing it the same as
a normal case of רוב. Rov. So those that would say you
would go by קרוב Karov against רוב Rov would say you would
go by קרוב Karov even against a case of רוב ומצוי, Rov
u'matzui, although that's really much harder to understand once a pattern has
been established. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, okay? So we're
still trying to defend this idea of going by רוב Rov and
certainly if it's רוב ומצוי. Rov u'matzui. איתמר. Itmar. Now we're going
to see if we can prove this again. חבית שצפה בנהר. Chavit
she'tzafah banahar.
You've got a barrel of wine that's floating in the river. אמר
רב נמצאת כנגד עיר שרובה ישראל מותר. Amar Rav nimtzet keneged ir
she'rubah Yisrael mutar.
So now it's basically it's like an אבידה, Aveidah, nobody is chasing
after it, you're allowed to keep it. The question is is it
סתם יינם Stam yeinam or not סתם יינם? Stam yeinam? Did it
come from Jews or not from Jews? So he says... If it's
floating by a city that's majority Jewish, then you assume it came
from that city. That's a קרוב karov and it's מותר. mutar. נמצא
כנגד עיר שרובה נכרים, Nimtza keneged ir sherubah nachrim, if the city's
majority non-Jewish, so in that case אסורה. asura. It's forbidden, אסורה, asura,
because you assume it comes from that city, you go by קרוב.
karov. ורמינהו, Varminhu, this is, but it's רוב rov here.
What, what do you mean go by קרוב? karov?
No, the רוב נכרים rov nachrim and the רוב ישראל rov Yisrael
mean... it's confusing... yeah, but it means, it means it's from this
city and not from one of the other cities that might be
along the way of the river. Okay, that's the city that is
nearby. Right, once you're within that, once you're attributing it to that
city, then you go by the majority people in that city. But
then there's no competition with רוב rov and קרוב. karov. The competition
here is nearby cities or the more, or the more numerous far
away cities. So רב Rav says, רב Rav says you assume it
comes from the nearby city and that determines whether it's a problem
with the wine or not. ושמואל אמר, uShmuel amar, אפילו נמצאת כנגד
עיר שרובה ישראל אסורה. afillu nimtzet keneged ir sherubah Yisrael asura. No,
even if it's opposite the city that's majority Jewish, presumably the majority
of the cities or the towns by on the river are non-Jewish,
and therefore the רוב rov is non-Jewish and you go by the
רוב, rov, not by the קרוב. karov. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so אימור
מהאי דקרא אתאי, eimor mehai Dikra ata, maybe it comes from this
city, apparently it's the name of a city, דקרא, Dikra, maybe it
comes from this non-Jewish city, you know, so you can't just assume
that it comes from the nearby city. So the גמרא Gemara says
לימא בדרבי חנינא קמיפלגי, leima b'deRabbi Chanina kamiflagi, let's say they debate
רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. מר אית ליה דרבי חנינא Mar it lei
deRabbi Chanina that אביי, Abaye, who is it, שמואל, Shmuel, excuse me,
that goes by רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, you go by the majority
and the majority of the cities are non-Jewish, ומר לית ליה דרבי
חנינא, u-mar leit lei deRabbi Chanina, and רב Rav goes by, rejects
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina and goes by the nearby city. That seems
a pretty reasonable debate, reasonable way of explaining the debate. אמר, Amar,
לא, lo, not necessarily, דכולי עלמא אית להו דרבי חנינא. de-kulei alma
it lehu deRabbi Chanina. Clearly the גמרא Gemara is working very hard
to defend רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, although there's sometimes good evidence that
you go by קרוב, karov, the גמרא Gemara really wants to push
the רוב rov idea. So everybody would hold you go by רוב.
rov. If everybody holds you go by רוב, rov, why does רב
Rav say you can go by the nearby city? והכא בהא
קמיפלגי, Ve-hacha be-ha kamiflagi, here's what they debate. מר סבר אי איתא
דמהאי דקרא אתאי, Mar savar i ita de-mehai Dikra ata, if it
really came from this דקרא, Dikra, city דקרא, Dikra, this non-Jewish city
from this far away city, אקולי ופשורי הוו מטפו לה. akulei u-pshurei
havu matpu lah. So the various obstacles in the river, you know,
רש״י Rashi says like the אקולי akulei like the protrusions, it would
have stopped before it got here. The פשורי pshurei are like the
still waters, like sometimes you have an inlet and it doesn't continue
to flow down the river. So there's a million ways it could
have been diverted before reaching here. So basically what רב Rav is
saying is, normally I would be concerned with רוב, rov, but here,
sort of like what the גמרא Gemara said before by the, what
do you call it, by the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, you know
the גמרא Gemara said you have big mountains and there's no access
to outside cities. So the גמרא Gemara saying here, it's most likely,
you know, the access of the outside cities upstream is much more
limited. Because anything that would... now we all know that's not true,
right, you know, like you find something downstream it could have come
from miles away. But the argument here is is that we're actually
going to discount the רוב rov that's distant because we're going to
say it has, that רוב rov has difficult access to this location.
And therefore that's the reason to discount it. Normally I would go
by רוב. rov. But when the access is difficult, then I'm going
to ignore it. Okay, ומר סבר u-mar savar and
you're going to go by קרוב. karov. Like the distant רוב rov
normally I would be concerned about, but if there are a lot
of obstacles I'm going to discount the concern of the distant רוב.
rov. ומר סבר u-mar savar and then שמואל Shmuel holds חריפא דנהרא
נקיט ואתי. charifa de-nahara nakit ve-atei. No, the power of the river
like, you know, it was held by the strength of the stream,
of the current, and that brought it here and that got over
the obstacles. Okay, but in principle the גמרא Gemara wants to again
affirm רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, everybody holds of רוב, rov, and the
question is just can we discount a far away רוב rov when
there are obstacles.
We still might be able to, but not from this example because
there's a strong current. Right.
Okay, yeah right, if there are clear obstacles like the גמרא Gemara
before about the case of the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, then we
would agree, but the question is when it's less clear.
Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says ההוא חצבא דחמרא, hahu chatzva de-chamra, now
you found a barrel of wine, דאשתכח בפרדיסא דערלה. de-ishtachach b'fardesa de-orlah.
And for some reason it was clear by the circumstances that this
had been stolen. That's not explicit in what's said, but that's the
assumption the גמרא Gemara is working with. Okay. And it was found
in a, you know, in a garden, in a vineyard of ערלה.
orlah. So do we assume that this wine was stolen from grapes
within the vineyard and therefore it's ערלה orlah wine or not? And
what can you do with the wine? So שרי רבינא, sharei Ravina,
רבינא Ravina said, "Yeah, you don't have to assume it's from the
grapes in this vineyard. It's permissible." So even though that was קרוב...
karov... Why would you...
I mean if someone
stole the
wine...
I was wondering about that
too, like, you know, like are we assuming that, like I was
trying to figure it out, are we assuming the guy... I assume
if you're taking a tour of the vineyard and you see some
like barrels of wine there you're gonna assume that the wine came
from that vineyard because they're growing it in the vineyard.
I assume the wine... press, right, I assume the wine press is
near the vineyard, right? You don't move it a lot, yeah.
So there's lots of, okay, like old wine presses, so rock-cut in
the mountains there. Right, right, right.
They're right there,
they're right there in the vineyard, right, near the vineyard, right. So
that seems to be the case. That we're assuming the actual wine
press is directly proximate or in the vineyard. And you found this
barrel of wine, so it's reasonable to assume, קרוב, Karov, that it
came from this vineyard and therefore it's ערלה. Orlah. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so where were we? שרי רבינא. Sharei Ravina. לימא משום
דסבר לה Leima mishum desavar lah to רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. He
holds like רבי
חנינא Rabbi Chanina that
even though it's קרוב, Karov, it's mamash in this vineyard, the majority
of vineyards are not ערלה. Orlah. Then it says, no, שאני התם.
Shani hatam. No, no, there we can generally he can even go
by קרוב, Karov, but there the evidence points in the opposite direction.
How does the evidence point in the opposite direction? דמיגנב מיניה אצנויי
בגוויה לא מצני. Demignav minei atsnuyei begaveih lo matsnei. That you don't,
if you're going to steal the wine, you're not going to hide
it in the same vineyard you stole it from. I guess 'cause
you're afraid you're going to get found out or something. I don't
know. רש״י Rashi says, if you look at רש״י, Rashi, five lines
from the bottom, אצנויי בגוויה לא מצני, Atsnuyei begaveih lo matsnei, אין
דרך הגנבים להצניע יין במקום שגנבוהו משם משום דמסתפי שמא
ימצאוהו דורכי הענבים. En derech haganavim lehatsnia yayin bemakom sheganvuhu misham mishum
demistafi shema yimtza'uhu dorechei ha'anavim. Right? The people that are stomping the
wine. I don't know, but if you hide it in another vineyard
it's not going to be found? I don't get the logic here.
Maybe in another vineyard they won't recognize it.
Oh, they won't recognize it. Okay, maybe that's true.
If you're in Napa Valley, by the way,
where you have small grapes, small vineyards or something like that. On
the other hand, they also tend to buy grapes from other vineyards.
Oh, that's interesting.
So this guy has, you know, the specific grapes that I want
to make, so I'll buy his grapes. Aha. So the fact that
it's from your thing
doesn't mean it's from your vineyard. Right. The גמרא Gemara is not
working with that assumption, but I hear that. So right, but apparently
it's in a type of a barrel that would be recognized that
it belonged to a particular vineyard, so you wouldn't hide it within
that vineyard itself because then you'll be found out. You would hide
it in a different vineyard.
And then it says, והני מילי חמרא, Vehanei milei chamra, that's only
the
barrel of
wine. אבל אנבי, Aval invei, if you had seen like a bunch
of grapes that apparently had been stolen, they were in some pouch
or something, מצני, Matsnei, then you would hide the bunch of grapes
within the same vineyard that you had stolen it, but not a
barrel of wine. Like, I don't, I don't understand this. So we're
just going to accept that. Okay, anyway, the fact that we're going
by assuming it's from another vineyard, the argument is, is not because
סתם Stam we go by רוב, Rov, but דוקא Davka the evidence
points to the fact that it's coming from an outside vineyard and
not this, because people wouldn't hide this in the same vineyard for
whatever reason. All right. הנהו זיקי דחמרא, Hanehu zikki dechamra, back to
another case of wine. There were flasks of wine דאשתכח בי כופאי,
De'ishtakach bei kufai, that were found in
between the vines. Again, so a similar to the barrel except here
it's a flask between the vines. שרינהו רבא. Shareinhu Rava. So רבא
Rava said
it's permissible, that you basically...
oh, because here wasn't the question of ערלה, Orlah, here was the
question of Jewish or non-Jewish. Okay, so this vineyard was owned by
Jews, even though the majority of vineyards were owned by non-Jews. Okay,
so he said look, if you find the flask of wine in
a Jewish vineyard you can assume it's Jewish, it's from the wine,
from this wine, and therefore it's not a סתם יינם Stam yeinam
problem. שרינהו רבא. Shareinhu Rava. לימא לא סבר לה כרבי חנינא? Leima
lo savar lah keRabbi Chanina? Maybe he doesn't hold of רבי חנינא?
Rabbi Chanina? He goes by קרוב Karov even though the majority of
the vineyards around here are owned by non-Jews. No, שאני התם דרובא
דשפוכי ישראל נינהו. Shani hatam deruba deshafochei Yisrael ninhu. No, no,
here it's different because even though in this area maybe most of
the vineyards are owned by non-Jews, most of the people that sort
of sell wine to, actually it's not just vineyards I think... let
me just check רש״י... Rashi...
Right, I'm sorry. No, it's not vineyards. The story is like this.
The story is is that let's assume that most of the vineyards
in this area are Jewish, but most of the people that pass
by, right, it's a majority non-Jewish population. Okay, so you've got your...
right
here's your vineyard, okay, and here's you know you found a flask
of wine, okay, in the vineyard, okay, and you've got all these
Jewish vineyards around here, but the story is is that this is
you know you're here in Napa Valley, it's a reverse Napa Valley
where it's all owned by Jews and the non-Jews are the visitors.
Okay. So the majority of the population that are coming by are
non-Jews. And everybody, of course, what do you bring when you bring
your drinks for your trip?
You bring a flask of wine. We're not talking about a barrel,
we're talking about a flask, right?
So here he says you consume it comes from this vineyard and
it's kosher and you don't have to assume it's coming from the
majority of people that bring flasks of wine through the area, because
a flask of wine is coming from a traveler, it's not coming
from something done in the vineyard, okay. So you don't have to
assume it comes from the majority of the travelers, which are not
Jewish. So it seems like you go by קרוב karov since right
directly here it's a Jewish space, you can assume it came from
like a Jew with the flask of wine and you don't have
to assume it's coming from
the non-Jew, the non-Jewish travelers.
And it's a flask, it's not a barrel. So it came from
somebody's personal like wine, right? So even though most of the people
here are Jewish, nevertheless or and the immediate environs are Jewish, the
רוב rov of the people that pass through are not Jewish and
you see you go by קרוב. karov.
And this doesn't really have to be a כרם kerem case, this
could be in a neighborhood.
It could be, but the case was a כרם. kerem. But it
could be. At least that's the way Rashi says בגיפי, begifei, Rashi
says תמנין בין גפיים שבכרם. tmanin bein gefayim shebakerem. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says so doesn't this show you go by
קרוב karov and not רוב? rov? So the גמרא Gemara says no.
Here's different דרובא דשלוחי ישראל נינהו. deruba deshluchei Yisrael ninhu. Most of
the people, Rashi says שלוחי shluchei are the people that are basically
selling little like filling up flasks of wine, the Jews got a
good business going because here there's you know there's all of these
non-Jewish travelers and they're going to visit all the vineyards or whatever.
So these the Jews have these little stores here, right? Here are
the Jews with their stores and they're filling up people's they're the
gas stations. They're filling up people's wine flasks for them. So yes,
the majority are non-Jews but the non-Jews are getting their wine flasks
filled by the Jews with kosher wine.
Once they're drinking from it is it still kosher?
Oh, that's a good question. Oh, that's good. Why? Is it would
it have to be like a sealed flask? Yeah, no, you're right.
I mean we're assuming not מבושל. mevushal.
That's a good question. Yeah. Weren't the נודות nodot aren't they reusable?
Like Rashi says שציפיין נכפה she-tzipayan nichpa
the נודות nodot עם כל ורדי דרכא. im kol vardei darcha. And
it's leather.
Yeah, they're reusable. Right. There's no way they're filling them up. The
Goy's bringing his נוד nod and the Jew is...
Yeah, he's
got like a a little wine kiosk.
No, I understand, but it's a really good question. Once they drink
from it, they make it not good. That's a good question. I
don't know. I'll have to see if there's some discussion about that.
Maybe it was filled to the top.
Yeah, right, that's what I meant, like it was clearly filled up
and hadn't been drunk from or something. I don't know, that's a
good question. But so we'll I'll have to look into that, but
for now the answer is let's
let's go with it for now, okay? So their flasks are being
filled by Jews. So the גמרא Gemara says והני מילי ברברבי. vehani
mili beravrevi. Now, that's only true though if you know if they
are like large flasks. אבל בזוטרי aval bezutrei if they're small flasks
אימא מדראחי נפלו. eima midrachei naflu. Then you then you assume that
that actually were people's personal flasks and they had their own wine.
If it's a large thing you're getting it filled up, you know,
from there and maybe that's also partly the answer to Jenna's question.
But not like if it's a large thing it's not a personal
one, you know, it's your storage or whatever, so then we're assuming
you're not drinking from it. But if it's a small personal flask,
you didn't get it that you maybe brought from home and that
does come from the non-Jews and that would be a problem. Okay,
but the גמרא Gemara says ואי איכא רברבי בהדייהו. ve-i ika ravrevi
behadayihu. Now let's say you found here a big flask and a
small one together, in that case אימא באברורי הוי מנחי. eima be-avrurei
hava manchei. So
Rashi says אברורי avrurei means it's like to balance the donkey. That
basically if you're donkey, you know, you get your big you know
storage tank filled up with wine here and you put it on
one side of the donkey, but then it like creates an imbalance.
So then what you're going to do is you're going to get
your small personal flasks filled up as well in order to create
to balance the load. So in that type of a case there
could be cases where the small personal flasks were also filled up
here, you know, and so if you see big flasks you assume
are filled up here and they come from the Jews. Small flasks
you assume are personal, they took them with them from home and
they're a problem. But if here you found a big flask and
a small flask together, then you assume that they were filled up
together here. And they were filled up to like balance the load
of the donkey. Is that sort of understandable? Okay, we're going to
go with that. But I still think that Jenna's question about once
you're dealing with a small flask, what about if they drank from
it, is a good one. We might we would have to I
guess assume that the evidence is that it hasn't been drunk from.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara sort of ends with having a
good evidence that sometimes it sees it seems that there is ברייתא
braita you know משניות mishnayot ברייתות braitot אמוראים amoraim that might say
you go by קרוב karov rather than רוב. rov. And in the
end the גמרא Gemara works very hard to defend רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina and to say that under normal circumstances you go by רוב,
rov, except there are always extenuating circumstances or special circumstances.
No, I mean that's a different question within the רוב rov discussion,
right. But this is all considered פרוש, parush, I mean all these
cases are basically פרוש. parush. Okay, so let's take a look now,
let's start the next משנה. mishnah. Back to more standard בבא בתרא
Bava Batra issues. מרחיקין את האילן מן העיר Marchikin et ha'ilan min
ha'ir עשרים וחמש אמה. esrim v'chamesh amah.
So a tree has to be 25 אמות amot away from a
city. Now we've already learned, I mean it's a coming up משנה,
mishnah, but we've mentioned it a few times that a tree has
to be away from a pit, 25 אמות amot because the roots
will go into the pit or a cistern, I should say. But
why does it have to be 25 אמות amot away from a
city is less clear, from where a town begins. We'll see about
that. ובחרוב ובשקמה U'v'charuv u'v'shikma חמישים אמה. chamishim amah. אבא שאול אומר
Abba Shaul omer כל אילן סרק kol ilan srak חמישים
אמה. chamishim amah. Any non-fruit bearing tree has to be 50 אמות
amot away. So basically just not to hold you all in such
terrible suspense, the גמרא Gemara is going to say that the reason
it has to be distant is because it just looks nice to
the city, that there's some open space before you start having the
trees, or nice to the town, near the town, okay. And therefore
אבא שאול Abba Shaul says, you know, since non-fruit bearing trees are
not as aesthetically pleasant, we want to keep them a little bit
more distant from the town. So therefore that's at least the way
רש"י Rashi says, חרוב ושקמה. charuv v'shikma. רש"י Rashi says אילן סרק
גנאי הוא
לעיר. ilan srak gnai hu la'ir.
So therefore we want to keep them a little more distant. רש"י
Rashi also explains that the reason, for example, the חרוב charuv and
the שקמה shikma have to be 50 אמות amot is because they
have wide and big branches, so you want to just create a
greater sense of space. You don't want to crowd the town to
have trees right nearby. You want there to be some space. Safety
concern? Safety, you
mean like a גנב ganav could hide in the forest or something?
Oh, that's interesting. I hadn't thought of that. רש"י Rashi emphasizes נויי
העיר, noy ha'ir, but that's an interesting perspective. Okay. ואם העיר קדמה
V'im ha'ir kadma קוצץ ואינו נותן דמים. kotzetz v'eino nosein damim.
If the town was there first and this person planted a tree
where he was not allowed, then you cut it down and you
don't even have to reimburse him. He was in violation. ואם אילן
קדם V'im ilan kadam קוצץ ונותן דמים. kotzetz v'nosein damim.
Now if the tree was there first and then the city was
built, so the person was not in violation, the people of the
town are still entitled to have their town look like it should
look, so they... this is a surprising idea. The guy with the
tree was not in violation, the town can still cut it down
and they would have to... but they would have to reimburse because
the guy wasn't in violation, but they're still entitled to cut it
down. ספק זה קדם ספק זה קדם קוצץ ואינו נותן דמים. Safek
zeh kadam safek zeh kadam kotzetz ve-eino noten damim.
If it's unclear, so the bias is always towards the town people.
They can cut it down and they don't have to pay. Okay,
so I... we'll get back and look at that because that last
section is particularly interesting, especially contrasted to a משנה mishnah coming up
about a case when it's between two people. So let's first look
at the גמרא's Gemara issue about why you have to keep the
tree separate. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why do you keep the tree
separate? אמר עולא משום נויי העיר. Amar Ulla mishum noy ha'ir.
Because of the beauty of the city, you want to have some
more open space before you start with
the trees. ותיפוק ליה דאין עושין שדה מגרש ולא מגרש שדה. V'teipuk
lei d'ein osin sadeh migrash v'lo migrash sadeh. So this is like
in the תורה Torah where it speaks about the ערי הלוים, arei
ha'Levi'im, it speaks about having fields, the שדה, sadeh, and before you
get the fields where you plant the wheat, you have מגרש, migrash,
which is like the open area, the lawns, and that's actually, what?
Green space, right. And that's like a thousand אמות. amot. Okay, not
25 אמות, amot, not 50 אמות, amot, a thousand אמות. amot. So
anyway, so why don't you say that that's the reason? If that
was the reason, anyway it would have to be much more than
25 אמות. amot. So you're not to have some green space outside
of the city and you're not allowed to turn it into planted,
and planted presumably means even planted with trees. So the גמרא Gemara
says, לא צריכא לרבי אליעזר Lo tzericha l'Rebbi Eliezer דאמר עושין שדה
מגרש ומגרש שדה. d'amar osin sadeh migrash u'migrash sadeh. No, we're going
according to רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer that says that that idea that
you have to have green space and then the field is only
in the תורה Torah by the שדי לויים, sdei Levi'im, only by
the Levite cities. By a normal city or normal town, you don't
have these parameters. A town can do what it wants, okay. So
therefore within that context, you know, that's why you can do it
up to 50 אמות amot or up to 25 אמות. amot. So
it says, and it has to be, you know, it's not this
absolute rule about שדה מגרש ומגרש שדה. sadeh migrash u'migrash sadeh. So
the גמרא Gemara says, דעושין שדה מגרש ומגרש שדה, הכא משום נויי
העיר לא עבדינן. d'osin sadeh migrash u'migrash sadeh, hacha mishum noy ha'ir
lo avdinan. But although in principle you don't have these strict rules
like you have by the ערי הלוים, arei ha'Levi'im, but you still
are entitled to a 25 אמות amot of unplanted space, okay. And
that's for נויי העיר. noy ha'ir. So that's why that applies to
all cities. ולרבנן נמי דאמרי אין עושין שדה מגרש ולא מגרש שדה.
U'l'Rabbanan nami d'amri ein osin sadeh migrash v'lo migrash sadeh. Now the
גמרא Gemara clarifies, by the way, even according to the רבנן Rabbanan
you might need the reason of our משנה. mishnah. Because even though
they say you're not allowed to turn the green space into a
field and vice versa, הני מילי זרעים. hanei mili zraim. That's only
if you want to plant the green space with like seeds, basically
you want to make it into a wheat field. That you're not
allowed to do. אבל אילנות עבדינן. Aval ilanos avdinan. But you can
plant trees in this מגרש, migrash, in this green space. Okay, and
since, which makes sense, right? You want a nice green space, that's
what like a nice park is. It's got trees, it's got open
green spaces and so on. So even for the רבנן, Rabbanan, the
only thing you can't do is you can't turn it into a
wheat field, but you could plant trees. So even if you say
you need to keep a thousand אמות amos as a מגרש, migrash,
okay, and that מגרש migrash can contain trees, but our משנה mishna
says the tree line can't begin until twenty-five אמות amos outside of
the city. Okay, so yes, you can have trees but it can't
begin right away. Okay, אבל אילנות עבדינן והכא משום נויה העיר לא,
aval ilanos avdinan ve-hacha mishum noye ha-ir lo, but because of the
beauty of the city, we don't allow the tree line to begin
within twenty-five אמות. amos. You need the first twenty-five אמות amos unplanted.
ומנא תימא דשאני בין זרעים ולאילנות, u-minah teima de-shani bein zera'im ve-ilanos,
now how do you know that once we want to sort of
have this sort of the quality of a certain type of a
space that having trees is more considered like, you know, like a
park-like space, more habitable than having like, you know, like wheat which
would change the nature of the space? How do you know that?
So דתניא de-tanya because we taught in a ברייתא brayta about הלכות
שבת. Hilchos Shabbos. קרפף יותר מבית סאתים שהוקף לדירה. karpef yoser mi-beis
sa'atayim she-hukaf le-dira. So this is actually one of the very important
הלכה halacha in הלכות עירוב, Hilchos Eiruv, which is the following. If
you have, you know, you make walls around an open space. So
we make it we make it with of course these like, you
know, posts and the strings and the צורת הפתח, tzuras hapesach, but
they're considered halachic walls. If the space is very large, יותר מבית
סאתים, yoser mi-beis sa'atayim, which is fifty אמות amos by a hundred
אמות, amos, five thousand square אמות. amos. So figure out what that
is, I don't know what it is, anyway. Fifty אמות amos about
seventy-five feet by a hundred and fifty feet, I don't know I
can't do the math. Between the posts. If you have a big
open space that's more than בית סאתים, beis sa'atayim, fifty אמות amos
by a hundred. Okay, that's a קרפף יותר מבית סאתים. karpef yoser
mi-beis sa'atayim. This is the בית סאתים, beis sa'atayim, okay, that's five
thousand square אמות. amos. Okay, if you have a space that big
and you put walls around it, right, so then it is then
you can then you can carry in it, it's a רשות היחיד.
reshus hayachid. If it's הוקף לדירה. hukaf le-dira. But if it's הוקף
שלא לדירה, hukaf shelo le-dira, if even with sort of the stuff
around it, it's not really made to be inhabited, like, well, you
know, let's say it was you were protecting a wheat field, that
would be an example of something that's לא הוקף לדירה. lo hukaf
le-dira. You want a wall, you want to protect it, you've got
your big fence around your multi-acre wheat field, okay, you can't carry
in it on שבת, Shabbos, because it's not considered like a רשות
היחיד. reshus hayachid. Because even though it has walls, it's too big
of a space and it's not made for being inhabited. Now I
have to tell you that this becomes a big issue by contemporary
עירובים, eiruvs, because contemporary עירובים, eiruvs, you've got a big, you know,
צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach around a large space, and let's say in
the middle of your space you've got, I don't know, a lake,
or you've got a park, or you've got a forest or something
like that. Okay, so that's not, you know, made for being inhabited.
So I mean in הלכות עירוב Hilchos Eiruv what you have to
know is people have very creative definitions of what הוקף לדירה hukaf
le-dira is. So like you can have like this huge pond, Central
Park, right, you've got a huge pond and nobody does anything in
the middle of the pond, it's more than בית סאתים, beis sa'atayim,
nobody is like doing any habitable type of activities, but they say
no, because since people float boats at the edge of the pond,
okay, that's considered to be הוקף לדירה hukaf le-dira because it's being
used by the inhabitants, even though you're not using the main part,
you're using this little part of it, right? So it becomes very
what? Right? Not the reservoir. Not the reservoir, well not the reservoir
would be a good קשיא. kasha. Anyway it becomes very interesting how
do you define הוקף לדירה, hukaf le-dira, okay? So you know the
fact you've got this big forest, but yeah but sometimes people take
walks in the forest, right, where exactly you draw the line? Whatever
would be a case of לא הוקף לדירה lo hukaf le-dira would
be hard to find in contemporary הלכות עירוב, Hilchos Eiruv, okay? But
anyway that's the הלכה. halacha. So let's take a look. So it
says, okay, ד... de... what? Did you have a little help in
New York if you can claim that someone has slept in any
given park? There you go. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. דתניא קרפף יותר מבית סאתים שהוקף לדירה, de-tanya karpef yoser mi-beis
sa'atayim she-hukaf le-dira, as it was surrounded for the purpose of being,
you know, inhabited. נזרע רובו, nizra rubo, now so now it's a
good רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. But you now decided to plant in
it, the majority of the space you've now planted. הרי הוא כגינה
ואסור, harei hu kegina ve-asur, if you planted it with like seeds
meaning like you made it into a wheat field, so now it's
a wheat field and now it's not considered הוקף לדירה hukaf le-dira
anymore because a wheat field is where your wheat grows, it's not
where you do any living type of activity. So now it is
no longer good and it's no longer רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. ניטע
רובו, nita rubo, if you planted the majority of it with trees,
הרי הוא כחצר ומותר, harei hu kachatzer u-mutar, then that's like a
yard, a courtyard. People spend, you know, they go they go for
walks in parks and they take their dogs and they have picnics.
So trees is still a habitable location place whereas a wheat field
is not considered habitable and that actually is, I wouldn't say it's
the same הלכה halacha as we're talking about but it makes sense
as a parallel, right? If you want to keep the space outside
of your city as a type of a, you know, as a
כזה, kaza, as a green space, as a like, you know, before
you start the business enterprise of the wheat, so trees is consistent
with that, it's a nice park green area and that's okay. A,
and therefore, even if you can't make a מגרש migrash into a
שדה, sadeh, trees is not making it into a שדה. sadeh. Okay,
but you still have to keep it 25 אמה amah away because
you need that a middle space for the, for the aesthetics of
the city. Okay, so now we turn to the next part of
our משנה. Mishnah. Now for the next part of our משנה, Mishnah,
I we really you need to compare it to the to a
coming up משנה. Mishnah. Because this משנה Mishnah says what? What does
this משנה Mishnah say? This משנה Mishnah says if the city comes
first, then it says what? Then you cut then you cut down
and and no money. Okay, if the tree comes first, it says
you cut down and you give the money. Okay, and if it's
a ספק, safek, it says קוצץ ואינו נותן דמים, kotzetz v'eino nosein
damim. cut down and no money. Okay, that's what this says. Now,
let's take a look at turn your page for a second because
the גמרא's Gemara going to make this comparison to the משנה Mishnah
on כ"ה עמוד ב'. chaf hei amud beis. Okay, and the משנה
Mishnah says the following: מרחיקין את האילן מן הבור כ"ה אמה, marchikin
es ha'ilan min habor esrim vechamesh amah, the same idea, a tree
25 אמה amah away from a בור. bor. ובחרוב ובשקמה חמשים אמה,
ubeyachar veshikmah chamishim amah, בין מלמעלה בין מן הצד. bein milemala bein
milatzad. Okay, same idea, the tree from the בור, bor, the tree
from the city. 50 and 25 אמות amot depending on what type
of tree. Now, אם הבור קדמה, im habor kadmah, if the if
the if the well came first, which is like here the city
came first, so if it's here the well comes first, so then
what does it say? אם הבור קדמה קוצץ ונותן דמים. im habor
kadmah kotzetz venotein damin. So then it says cut and you give
money. Okay, ואם האילן קדם לא יקוץ. ve'im ha'ilan kadam lo yikot.
And if the tree is first in this משנה, Mishnah, it says
don't cut. Okay, this is getting a little confusing, I need to
separate. ואם ספק, ve'im safek, it says ואם ספק, ve'im safek, what
does it say? לא יקוץ. lo yikot. Okay, so you look down
this, right? We're our in in our משנה Mishnah with the city,
the city is much more has a much greater advantage because it's
a city, you're always going to cut it down and the only
question is are you going to pay for it? Right? And you're
not going to pay if the city is in the right and
you will pay if the city is not in the right, so
the ספק safek the benefit goes to the city. In the case
of the well, okay, there you know, it's favor the tree well
or it's more balanced at least, right? In the case of the
well, there are cases where you're not going to cut down you're
not going to cut down the tree what? You're not either you're
not going to cut it down or if you cut it down
you pay. Exactly, exactly. The tree is not a city. I mean
rather so that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to look at.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so גמרא
Gemara says like this: ואם עיר קדמה קוצץ ואינו נותן דמים. ve'im
air kadma kotzetz ve'eino notein damin. מאי שנא גבי בור דקתני קוצץ
ונותן דמים mai shna gabei bor de-katani kotzetz venotein damin? So here
come here, how come it says how come it says you don't
pay and in the case of the well when you know here
when you're in rights, when you're in rights you don't even have
to pay. Here even when you're in rights you have to pay.
So why do you have to pay in that case? Okay, אמר
רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, קדרא דבי שותפי לא חמימי ולא קרירי.
kidra de-bei shutfei lo chamimei velo kerirei. This is a great line
in the גמרא. Gemara. A pot watched by committee, right, you know
the line they say you know what is a camel a horse
designed by committee? So a pot watched by committee does not get
too hot and does not get too cold. Okay, nobody's ever completely
irresponsible, but nobody really makes sure the job gets done the way
it needs to get done. So if you have distributed responsibility, it's
not going to get done so well. So therefore what does that
mean? That means the way it's a strange answer. We're going to
give a better answer in a minute, but this answer is because
you're here dealing with a lot of people in the city, okay
I should say town, anyway, it's not clear that it's going to
take a while to get the town to pay up if they
need to pay. Alright, and since because you know it's a lot
of people, nobody's going to want to pay. So if you would
demand that they would pay, then they would never get around to
cutting it down because then nobody the they're not going to be
able to raise the money to pay. And since we want the
town not to have these trees by it, it's sort of like
your irresponsibility winds up benefiting you. Since it's going to be hard
for us to get you to pay, but we want to get
the tree down, we're going to say you don't have to pay.
Alright, so it's a logistic kind of answer or a it's a
cautionary answer. Yes, but the גמרא's Gemara going to give a better
one. The better answer is that we the town has more rights
than a private owner. That's really the better what the גמרא's Gemara
going for. ומאי קושיא, umai kushya, big deal, דילמא שאני היזק דרבים
מהיזק דיחיד. dilma shani hezek de-rabbim me-hezek de-yachid. There's a much better
answer, right? Here everybody in the town is being... damaged, is being,
and if the town is in its rights, it shouldn't have to
pay at all. Here the case of an individual, it's not seen
as severe. So yes, you're in your rights to cut it down,
but he's still losing his tree, paying for his tree. אלא אם
דרב כהנא סיפא איתמר. Ella im d'Rav Kahana seifa itmar. The reason
for this is because the town has more rights and they're able
to cut it down without paying, it's a majority. Rav, this was
said on the second case, אסיפא איתמר: aseifa itmar: אילן קדם קוצץ
ונותן דמים. Ilan kadam kotzetz ve-noten damim. So if the tree comes
first, you cut and you pay money. ולימא להו הבו לי ברישא
דמי והדר אקוץ. Ve-leima le-hu havu li be-reisha demei ve-hadar ekotz. So
now, without comparing it to the other משנה, Mishnah, why do you
first cut down and then pay money? Let's say the guy says,
I want you to pay me my money first and then I'll
let you cut it down. Why are you entitled to cut it
down and pay later? אמר רב כהנא קדירא דבי שותפי לא חמימא
ולא קרירא. Amar Rav Kahana Kidra de-bei shutfei la chamima ve-la kerira.
No, because again, it's still ironic because it's your bad behavior that
rewards you, but if we allow this person to demand money first
before cutting it down, you might never get around to cutting it
down because you're going to have a hard time raising money. So
what we'd rather you do is cut it down first and owe
him the money. And even though that means that it might take
him a long time to get paid, we'd rather him have to
wait a long time to get paid and have the tree cut
down than not have the tree cut down. So this issue about
the what do you call it about the, it's hard to get
you guys to pay, explains why we allow you to first cut
it down and then pay. I mean, obviously, we would be inclined
to say the exact opposite: the guy would say it's going to
be so hard to get you all to pay, I need to
get paid first before I let you cut it down. But because
we are biased towards the benefit of the town of not having
the tree nearby, we allow them to cut down and pay first.
And now we get to the last line of the משנה: Mishnah:
ספק זה קדם ספק זה קדם Safek zeh kadam safek zeh kadam
קוצץ ואינו נותן דמים. kotzetz ve'eino notein damin, מאי שנא מבור דאמרת
לא יקוץ? Mai shna mi-bor d'amart lo yakotz? So here, if there's
a doubt, you cut down and you don't pay, right? It totally
benefits the city. Here, if there's a doubt, you don't cut; it
benefits the owner of the tree. So which one do we do?
So the גמרא Gemara says: התם דודאי לאו למקץ קאי ספקא נמי
לא אמרינן ליה קוץ. Hatam devadai lav lemakatz kai safeka nami lo
amrinan leh kotz. Because here it says in the case of the
בור, bor, okay, if
it was certain
the tree came first, what's the הלכה halacha here? If it's certain
the tree comes first, you don't cut the tree. So basically it's
like a המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi me-chavero alav hara'aya. We don't
know which one came first. If my tree came first, you wouldn't
be allowed to cut it down, so you have to bring proof
if you want to cut it down. So since you don't know,
don't cut, because if I'm right, if my tree did come first,
you wouldn't be allowed to. You want it cut down, you prove
it. In this case, however, we're always going to cut it down,
right? Whichever comes first, we're always going... so I'm entitled to cut
it down. So now the question is, do you
have to pay or not pay? Oh, now it's המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה. hamotzi me-chavero alav hara'aya. Okay.
הכא דודאי למקץ קאי אידי ואידי אמרינן ליה קוץ. Hacha devadai lemakatz
kai eidi ve-eidi amrinan leh kotz. Either way you're going to cut
it down. ספקא נמי אמרינן ליה קוץ. Safeka nami amrinan leh kotz.
So either way you get to cut it down. ואי משום דמי
אמרינן ליה אייתי ראיה ושקול. Ve-im mishum d'mei amrina leh ayis raya
u-shkol. So now prove that I have to pay you. Okay? So
because we've already established that the town has more rights, they're always
entitled to cut it down, therefore in a ספק safek they also
cut it down. It's true, sometimes they have to pay, but you
can't prove it's that case, so you don't have to pay. Whereas
in the case of the individual, you're only going to cut it
down if he is in the wrong. If he's in the right,
you're not going to cut it down. So therefore, when you don't
know, you then he has the, you have to prove that you
have a right to cut it down. And since you can't, you
leave it standing. Okay, well that's where we'll end with for today.